Finding Aid for Charles F. Bates papers, 1861-1888
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles F. Bates papers 1861-1888
Bates, Charles F. (Charles Franklin), d. 1922.
0.75 linear feet and 1 microfilm roll
85747 Aa 2
Dexter, Michigan, farmer and chairman of the Washtenaw County Committee of the Greenback Party. Correspondence concerning activities of Greenback Party in county, particularly relating to election of 1878, and other papers concerning the Bates family during the Civil War.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received in part from Mrs. Eugene J. Mann (donor no. 3745 ).
No furhter additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Charles Franklin Bates was born ca. 1840 in Dexter, Michigan. He enlisted in the 20th Michigan Infantry Company D on August 9, 1862 with formal induction occurring nine days later. On January 18, 1863 Bates was discharged in Washington, D.C. on a surgeon's certificate of disability.
Following the Civil War, Bates was a successful farmer and sawmill owner in Dexter. During the 1870s and 1880s, Bates was a Knights of Labor activist and chair of the Washtenaw County Committee of the Greenback Party.
He married Belvia Shearer and had two sons, Vernon and H. Carl. Charles Franklin Bates died in 1922.
The Charles Franklin Bates collection consists of correspondence, clippings, and miscellaneous relating to his war-time service and to his activities with the Knights of Labor and the Greenback Party. The collection is arranged into three series: Correspondence, Correspondence - Family, and Topical Files. Of particular interest is the Greenback Party correspondence which discusses the party's strategies, meetings, and speakers in the Ann Arbor area, the 1878 election, and local figures in the party. A letter, November 2, 1878, includes comments on the potential black vote for the Greenback party in the coming election. Much of the correspondence conveys personal and business information about Bates, especially correspondence with Emma and DeForest Lichfield and Gilett Salmon. There is, however, also letters about the Knights of Labor, especially a letter, 1886, from T.V. Powderly.
The microfilm is a duplicate of Greenback's Party correspondence folder with additional correspondence of family and friends.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Dexter (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1878.; Elections--Michigan--1886.; Greenback Labor Party (U.S.); Knights of Labor.; Michigan--Politics and government--1866-1876.; Michigan--Politics and government--1877-1898.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 20th (1862-1865). Company D.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Contributors:
Field, Moses W., 1828-1889.; Hampton, Charles S., 1856-1917.; Innes, Wm. P. (William Powers), 1826-1893.; Markey, Daniel P., b. 1857.; Mayo, Perry, 1839-1921.; Morrow, James H.; Parker, Sampson, b. 1818.; Michigan State Grange.; Perry, George B., b. 1839.; Potter, John M.; Powderly, Terence Vincent, 1849-1924.
- Correspondence
  - Balcom, Willie V., 1872 (Box 1)
  - Burden, Amos, 1841-1860 (Box 1)
  - Dickerson, Lewis P., 1871-1879 (Box 1)
  - Greenback Party, 1878-1888 (includes clippings) (Box 1)
  - Holden (J.J. and Lottie), 1866-1868 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    (arranged alphabetically within folder)
  - Salmon, Gilett, 1878-1888 (Box 1)
  - Sawmill sale, 1872-1881 (Box 1)
  - Williams, W.W., 1878 (Box 1)
  - Selections from the Correspondence series, including Greenback Party file; also some letters not found in the original papers (Reel 1)
- Family correspondence
  - Bates, E., 1863 (Box 1)
  - Bates, H., 1861 (Box 1)
  - Bates, Mary, 1861-1867 (Box 1)
  - Davis, F., 1871 (Box 1)
  - Litchfield (Emma and DeForest), 1862-1868 (Box 1)
  - Reynolds, Rhoda, 1862-1869 (Box 1)
  - Wilhelm, Carrie, 1861 (Box 1)
  - Wilhelm, George, 1858-1888 (Box 1)
  - Wilhelm, Thomas, 1862-1870 (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  - Clippings and newspapers, 1875-1887 and undated (Box 1)
  - Deeds, indentures, and receipts (Box 1)
  - Knights of Labor (rules and dues receipts), 1885-1887 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Army Infantry, 20th Regiment, 1878 and undated (Box 1)